LIHAO LIU

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests are Video Processing and Medical Image Analysis. Specifically, I focus on using Machine Learning techniques to solve surgical video processing, and video shadow detection tasks. Besides, I am also working on unsupervised medical image registration and segmentation tasks.

EDUCATION

University of Cambridge

Cambridge, UK

Ph.D. in Applied Mathematics

Oct. 2020 - Present

- Research Group: Cambridge Image Analysis Group

Expected Graduation: Spet. 2024

- Supervisor: Carola-Bibiane Schönlieb, Angelica I. Aviles-Rivero

- Ph.D. Award: Girton College Ph.D. Scholarship & GSK Ph.D. Fellowship

Chinese University of Hong Kong

Hong Kong SAR

M.Phil. in Computer Science and Engineering

Aug. 2017 - Jul. 2020

- Supervisor: Pheng-Ann Heng

- M.Phil. Award: CUHK M.Phil. Student Scholarship

Chongqing University

Chongqing, China

B.Eng. in Software Engineering

Sep. 2012 - Jul. 2016

D. Ling. in Software Engineering

- Ranking: Top 10% in Department

- B.Eng. Award: Outstanding Student in Chongqing University

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Microsoft Research Cambridge, UK

Research Intern at Healthcare Intelligence Group

Jun. 2021 - Aug. 2021

- I joined the InnerEye project, and worked with Ozan Oktay.

- I focused on cross-modality self-supervised data alignment tasks, especially for Chest X-ray applications.

University of Cambridge

Cambridge, UK

Visiting Student at Cambridge Image Analysis Group

Feb. 2020 - Jul. 2020

- I designed a basic registration-based unsupervised segmentation model for brain images.

Imsight Technology
Research Intern at AI for Medical Imaging Group

Aug. 2017 - Oct. 2017

Shenzhen, China

- I designed and developed the DeepLung software, and deployed it to multiple hospitals in Beijing for clinical usage.

Chinese University of Hong Kong

Hong Kong SAR

Junior Research Assistant at Medical Imaging Lab (CUMed)

Feb. 2017 - Jul. 2017

- I developed and integrated the deep learning algorithms into ITK-SNAP for lung nodule analysis.

[video demo]

Weiboyi Technology Co., Ltd

Beijing, China

Data Mining Engineer at Big Data Group

May. 2016 - Feb. 2017

- I developed a hive-based auto-update system for big files storing and updating.

PUBLICATIONS [Google Scholar]

SCOTCH and SODA: A Transformer Video Shadow Detection Framework

Lihao Liu, Jean Prost, Lei Zhu, Nicolas Papadakis, ..., and Angelica I Aviles-Rivero.

Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR), 2023.

[paper][project]

TrafficCAM: A Versatile Dataset for Traffic Flow Segmentation

Zhongying Deng, Yanqi Chen, Lihao Liu, ..., and Angelica I Aviles-Rivero.

Under Review at International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV), 2023.

[paper][project]

Why Deep Surgical Models Fail?: Revisiting Surgical Action Triplet Recognition through the Lens of Robustness

Yanqi Cheng, Lihao Liu, Shujun Wang, Yueming Jin, Carola-Bibiane Schönlieb, Angelica I. Aviles-Rivero.

Trustworthy Machine Learning for Healthcare (ICLR-TML4H), 2023. [paper][project]

PC-SwinMorph: Patch Representation for Unsupervised Medical Image Registration and Segmentation

Lihao Liu, Zhening Huang, Pietro Liò, Carola-Bibiane Schönlieb, and Angelica I Aviles-Rivero.

Under Review at IEEE Transactions on Medical Imaging (TMI, IF: 10.048), 2023.

You Only Look at Patches: A Patch-wise Framework for 3D Unsupervised Medical Image Registration

Lihao Liu, Zhening Huang, Pietro Liò, Carola-Bibiane Schönlieb, and Angelica I Aviles-Rivero.

Biomedical Image Registration (WBIR), 2022.

CoNIC Challenge: Pushing the Frontiers of Nuclear Detection, Segmentation, Classification and Counting

Simon Graham, Quoc Dang Vu, Lihao Liu, Chengyang Hong, and et. al.

Under Review at Medical Image Analysis (MIA, IF: 13.83), 2023.

[paper][code]

Simultaneous Semantic and Instance Segmentation for Colon Nuclei Identification and Counting

Lihao Liu, Chengyang Hong, Angelica I Aviles-Rivero, and Carola-Bibiane Schönlieb.

Medical Image Understanding and Analysis (MIUA), 2022.

[Merit NVIDIA Paper Award in MIUA-2022!] [Ranking 4/373 in the Grand Challenge CoNIC-2022!]

Domain Generalisation for Mammography Classification

Yijun Yang, Shujun Wang, Lihao Liu, Angelica I Aviles-Rivero, and Carola-Bibiane Schönlieb.

Under Review at Nature Machine Intelligence, 2022.

[coming soon]

[paper][code]

[paper]

[paper]

Unsupervised Lung CT Image Registration via Stochastic Decomposition of Deformation Fields

Jing Zou, Youvi Song, *Lihao Liu*, Angelica I Aviles-Rivero, Jing Oin.

Under Review at IEEE Transactions on Medical Imaging, (TMI, IF: 10.048), 2022.

[coming soon]

Deformable Lung CT Registration by Decomposing Large Deformation

Jing Zou, Lihao Liu, Youyi Song, Kup-Sze Choi, Jing Qin.

Biomedical Image Registration (WBIR), 2022.

[paper][code]

Contrastive Registration for Unsupervised Medical Image Segmentation

Lihao Liu, Angelica I Aviles-Rivero, and Carola-Bibiane Schönlieb.

Under Review at IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems (TNNLS, IF: 14.26), 2022. [paper][code]

Ψ-Net: Stacking Densely Convolutional LSTMs for Sub-cortical Brain Structure Segmentation

Lihao Liu, Xiaowei Hu, Lei Zhu, Chi-Wing Fu, Jing Qin, and Pheng-Ann Heng.

IEEE Transactions on Medical Imaging (TMI, IF: 10.048), 2020.

[paper][code]

Probabilistic Multilayer Regularization Network for Unsupervised 3D Brain Image Registration

Lihao Liu, Xiaowei Hu, Lei Zhu, and Pheng-Ann Heng.

Medical Image Computing and Computer Assisted Intervention (MICCAI), 2019.

[paper][code]

Multi-Task Deep Model with Margin Ranking Loss for Lung Nodule Analysis

Lihao Liu, Qi Dou, Hao Chen, Jing Qin, and Pheng-Ann Heng.

IEEE Transactions on Medical Imaging (TMI, IF: 10.048), 2019.

[paper][code]

MTMR-Net: Multi-Task Deep Learning with Margin Ranking Loss for Lung Nodule Analysis

Lihao Liu, Qi Dou, Hao Chen, Iyiola E. Olatunji, Jing Qin, and Pheng-Ann Heng.

Deep Learning in Medical Image Analysis (MICCAI-DLMIA), 2018.

[paper][code]

HONORS & AWARDS

- ICIAM FS1 Travel Award - Tokyo	March. 2023
- NoMADS Secondments for UCLA Visting Graduate Researcher - NoMADS	Jan. 2023
- Merit NVIDIA Paper Award - MIUA	July. 2022
Smith Knight and Paylaigh Knight Essay Prizes University of Cambridge	$M_{ar} = 2022$

 Smith-Knight and Rayleigh-Knight Essay Prizes - University of Cambridge Mar. 2022

- Ranking 4/373 in the Grand Challenge CoNIC-2022 Mar. 2022

- GSK Ph.D. Scholarship - GlaxoSmithKline (GSK) Aug. 2020 - Girton College Ph.D. Scholarship - University of Cambridge
 - Research Funding for Visiting Student - University of Cambridge
 - CUHK M.Phil. Student Scholarship - Chinese University of Hong Kong
 - Outstanding Student Award - Chongqing University
 - Qiu Shi Scholarship - Chongqing University
 - Sept. 2014

ACADEMIC ACTIVITIES

Invited Talks:

- SIAM Conference on Imaging Science, "Contrastive Registration for Unsupervised Image Segmentation", Mar. 2022.
- Chongqing University, "How Registration can Help to Segment Medical Images without Ground Truths?", Nov. 2021.
- East China Normal University, "Deep Learning Application in Medical Image Anaylsis", Nov. 2020.

Paper Review:

- MICCAI, IEEE TMI, MIA, CVPR, ICCV, ECCV

Teaching Assistant:

- CSCI2100 Data Structures	2019 - 2020	Spring
- CSCI3160 Design and Analysis of Algorithms	2018 - 2019	Fall
- CSCI3160 Design and Analysis of Algorithms	2017 - 2018	Fall

Volunteer Experience:

- I am the webpage manager and event in-person volunteer in MIUA conference and Women in MIUA workshop.
- I am an in-person volunteer in GeoMedIA workshop.